<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">    <!-- Channel name and description -->
    <channel>
        <title>OnlyRSS</title>
        <link>https://onlyrss.org</link>
        <description>OnlyRSS started out as an RSS feed with no associated website. The articles only existed in the feed and they could only be accessed via an RSS reader. But, as I became interested in article design, I started to hand code articles in HTML and CSS, with each article having it's own unique design.</description>        <!-- Channel image for RSS aggregators -->
        <image>
            <url>https://onlyrss.org/images/logo.png</url>
            <title>OnlyRSS</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org</link>
        </image>        <!-- Blog articles -->



        <!-- Tops 2021 -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article11</guid>
            <title>Why I prefer the Kindle</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/why-i-prefer-the-kindle.html</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2022 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[
<body>

<h1>Why I prefer the Kindle over physical books</h1>

    <p><strong>
    If you are reading this in your RSS Reader, then well done, RSS is cool,
     and therefore, by extension, so are you!. But, much of this article won't
      make sense unless you visit the actual blog post, as much of the article is inside a mock-Kindle that I created with CSS. </strong>
    </p>
<hr>
    <p>
      I created this article for two reasons: I wanted to highlight some
      Kindle benefits that are often overlooked (probably because they are
      specific to me), and I wanted to attempt some CSS that was a bit more
      adventurous than my usual tweaks to font and paragraph styles.
    </p>

    <p>
      My aim was to try and reproduce the Kindle Oasis reading experience as
      best I could (given my limited knowledge of CSS). The article is
      contained within the Kindle below. Use the Kindle's navigation buttons
      (on the right of the device) to page through the article. At the bottom
      of this page I've described what I learnt while creating my
      "mock-Kindle".
    </p>


          <h2>Background</h2>

          <p>
            I didn't used to read. Don't get me wrong, I had books, almost
            enough to fill a shelf (it was a mix of physics text books and a
            small but treasured collection of Calvin & Hobbes) but I wasn't "a
            reader". I didn't go to bed with a book, and picking up a book
            during the day was not part of my routine.
          </p>

          <p>
            This all changed about 7 years ago when I made a deal with a
            colleague, if she watched the TV show Firefly, then I'd read a
            book that she had recommended. I read that book on a Kindle, and I
            have barely put the Kindle down since. I'm not saying that I only
            kept up the habit of reading because of the Kindle, but I'm not
            sure I would have carried on if I had to order books, wait for
            them to arrive, and then struggle to read them in the dark while
            the wife tried to go to sleep next to me.
          </p>

          <p>
            The first device I bought was the Paperwhite, then I passed that
            onto the wife and I got a newer version of the Paperwhite, and a
            while later I bought an even newer generation Paperwhite, more
            recently I treated myself and upgraded to a Kindle Oasis.
          </p>

          <h2>benefits</h2>

          <h3>1 - The dictionary</h3>

          <p>
            Unlike Donald Trump, I don't <em>know all the words</em>, so being
            able to press my fingertip on a word and see the definition is
            great. Even more useful than the dictionary is the etymology, I
            find that learning how a word came to be helps me to remember its
            definition.
          </p>

          <h3>2 - The backlight</h3>

          <p>
            I mostly read in bed, and unlike my wife, I don't fall asleep as
            soon as my head hits the pillow, so the backlight on the Kindle is
            essential for me. On the Oasis you have the added benefit of adjusting the colour
            temperature, and switching to dark mode.
          </p>

          <h3>3 - The clock!</h3>

          <p>
            Ok, this one might seem a bit silly, but as I read when I go to
            bed, it's useful for me to keep an eye on the time, otherwise I
            might find myself reading well into the small hours. Like many
            people these days I don't have a clock in the bedroom as I rely on
            my phone. Having the clock on the Kindle stops me periodically
            reaching for my phone.
          </p>

          <h3>4 - Saving quotes</h3>

          <p>
            Not so important when reading fiction (which represents about 80%
            of what I read), but when I do venture into the world of
            non-fiction, I often like to save quotes or other useful sections
            of text so I can easily find them again later. This is a feature
            of the Kindle that often gets overlooked.
          </p>

          <h3>5 - Kindle Unlimited</h3>

          <p>
            Kindle Unlimited in the UK costs £7.99 pm and includes more than
            650,000 books that can be borrowed (up to 20 at a time). Of the 4
            books I read per month, probably 2-3 of those I've borrowed via
            Kindle Unlimited, so for me it easily makes financial sense.
          </p>

          <h3>6 - Whisper sync</h3>

          <p>
            This is Amazon's name for the feature that lets you sync your
            reading progress across Kindle devices and Kindle apps. When I
            find myself in the car waiting for one of my kids to finish
            [insert name of activity that seems really important to them now
            but they will quit once they become a teenager here], then I'll
            often fire up the Kindle app on my phone, and start reading where
            I'd finished off the night before.
          </p>

          <h3>7 - Font size</h3>

          <p>
            Being a man of a "certain age", I'd recently noticed that my arms
            were no longer long enough to allow my eyes to focus on objects
            held in my hands. For a little while, increasing the font size on
            the Kindle allowed me to put off the inevitable purchase of
            reading glasses.
          </p>

          <h3>8 - Time left in chapter</h3>

          <p>
            You have some options when it comes to what's displayed in the
            page footer on the Kindle, you can choose from the following:
            nothing, page number, time left in chapter, time left in book, and
            loc (like page number, but is independent of your style choices
            e.g. font-size etc.). As I don't like to stop reading mid-chapter, the length of a chapter is a metric I use
            when determining whether or not I'll start a chapter.
          </p>

          <h3>9 - Ergonomics</h3>

          <p>
            You can only read one page at a time, but with physical books you
            are forced to always have 2 pages on display, so you're always
            holding something that is twice the size it actually needs to be.
          </p>

          <p>
            There's also no distortion due to the page curving in towards the
            spine of the book (there's also no spine to break!).
          </p>

          <h3>10 - Dark mode</h3>

          <p>
            When it comes to dark mode on my PC and mobile apps I tend to
            leave it off. But, when it comes to the Kindle, I do prefer to
            turn dark mode on. As I read at night I always use the Kindle's
            backlight, and in dark mode, there's just less light being emitted.
            At the end of the day, it's the letters I want illuminated, not
            the background.
          </p>

    <h2>What I learnt</h2>

    <h3>It's time to go back to formula</h3>

    <p>
      My CSS "skills" are far worse than I thought. I'm comfortable enough
      with the typical CSS required for defining the style of a typical
      article body (which is one of the main reasons why I started this blog),
      but when it comes to using CSS for layout, I really don't know what I'm
      doing. Creating the Kindle above with CSS was more the result of trial
      and error, than it was me actually knowing what I was doing. So I'll be
      looking out for some CSS layout tutorials in the near future.
    </p>

    <h3>Tabular numerals are not just for tables</h3>

    <p>
      Tabular (as opposed to proportional) numerals are numerals where each figure takes up the same width.
      i.e. 1111 takes up the same with as 0000. This is important in tables, where users are comparing values that are
      stacked vertically. Basically, you want the hundreds, tens, units etc. to all be aligned vertically (for more
      details see <a href="https://creativepro.com/typetalk-know-your-figures/">this article)</a>.
    </p>

    <p>
      While creating the
      Kindle above, it occurred to me that tabular numerals should be used within body text when the numerical value
      can change dynamically. If tabular numerals are not used, then as the number changes value (and therefore also
      width), the proceeding content
      can shift horizontally, potentially leading to a word slipping onto the next line (OMG THE HORROR!!!). My case was
      a little less
      dramatic, and was related to the page number and percentage read indicators in the footer. Without tabular
      numerals, moving from page 1 to page 2 resulted in a small shift of the percentage read indicator. Not a big
      deal, but it taught me that tabular numerals are not just for tables. You can see this in action below, the top
      example uses non-tabular numerals (i.e. proportional), the bottom example uses tabular numerals.
    </p>

    <p><img src="https://onlyrss.org/images/why-i-prefer-the-kindle-notabnum.gif" alt="example showing the movement associated when using non-tabular numerals"></p>
    <p><img src="https://onlyrss.org/images/why-i-prefer-the-kindle-tabnum.gif" alt="example showing the lack of movement when using non-tabular numerals"></p>

    <h3>Separating paragraphs</h3>

    <p>
      This article made me think about how paragraphs are visually
      distinguished from one another. I'm a fan of some extra padding between
      paragraphs, but, while trying to make the Kindle text look as authentic
      as possible, I realised that most of the Kindle books I've read have no
      extra vertical space between paragraphs, but rather, they indent the
      first line of each paragraph (which makes sense I guess, as it doesn't
      waste any vertical space, which is important on devices such as
      eReaders). This is how paragraphs are separated in the "book" above.
    </p>

    <p>
      This wasn't new to me obviously, but what I hadn't noticed was that when
      indentation is used, it's usually omitted for the first paragraph in a
      section/chapter (this also makes sense, there's no paragraph directly
      above from which to be separated, and if the chapter heading is
      left-aligned, then both heading and the start of the paragraph are
      nicely aligned along the left margin, and we humans like stuff that is
      nicely aligned).
    </p>

    <p>
      At first I thought I would have to create a new paragraph class in CSS
      specifically for the first paragraph of each section (that removed the
      default paragraph indent), and then add the class manually, but it turns
      out that CSS has an easy solution for this.
    </p>

    <code> p + p { text-indent: 1.5em; } </code>

    <p>
      The "+" above means that the style (the text-indent in this example) is
      only applied to paragraphs directly proceeding other paragraphs.
    </p>

    <p>
      Conversely, if you wanted to apply a specific style to the first
      paragraph only, i.e. the paragraph directly proceeding a heading e.g.
      Heading 1, then the CSS selector would be:
    </p>

    <code> h1 + p { ... } </code>

    <h3>Using the :target selector to show hidden content</h3>

    <p>
      I haven't started to learn JavaScript (JS) yet, and as the purpose of
      this blog is for me to learn some basic web dev, it shouldn't (yet)
      include any JS. Unfortunately, the page navigation used above for the
      Kindle requires JS,...sort of.
    </p>

    <p>
      I did manage to create a version of the Kindle with working navigation
      that didn't require any JS, instead it took advantage of the :target
      pseudo selector in CSS, usually this is used to move the user to a
      specific section of a page after clicking on a link or button (e.g.
      creating a clickable Table of Contents). But, it can be used to
      selectively show page elements that are otherwise hidden.
    </p>

    <p>
      My non-JS version does work, but, it suffers from an unwanted
      "side-effect" (well, unwanted for my specific use case) i.e. it moves
      the page to the specific section (which is what it's meant to do!). You
      can see this in action when you select one of the nav buttons in the
      CodePen below (you also have to click on the start link first). So in
      the end I decided to create this page using JS, even though I had to ask
      a friend to provide the required JS.
    </p>

    <p>
      My non-JS implementation can be seen in the following CodePen. But
      you'll find a better description of how to use the :target selector to
      show hidden contents
      <a href="https://css-tricks.com/a-whole-website-in-a-single-html-file" target="_blank">here</a>.
    </p>

    <p class="codepen" data-height="700" data-default-tab="result" data-slug-hash="eYGVXOm" data-user="dbssticky">
      <span>
        See the Pen
        <a href="https://codepen.io/dbssticky/pen/eYGVXOm">
          Only RSS - Kindle (No JS)</a>
        by mark evans (<a href="https://codepen.io/dbssticky">@dbssticky</a>)
        on <a href="https://codepen.io">CodePen</a>.</span>
    </p>


</body>

]]>            </description>
        </item>

        <!-- Tops 2021 -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article10</guid>
            <title>Tops of 2021</title>
            <link></link>
            <pubDate>wed, 29 Dec 2021 17:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[
<body>
<h1>2021 Tops</h1>
<p>There's no web article associated with this RSS entry. This post exists in the RSS feed only. If you're reading this, you are a member of a very, very, small club.</p>

<p>Every year a group of friends and I exchange our 'Top's of the year'. Here's my list for 2021.</p>

<h2>Movies (first watched during 2021)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Promising Young Woman</li>
<li>Captain Fantastic</li>
<li>Nobody</li>
<li>Predestination</li>
<li>The Invisible Man</li>
<li>The Dig</li>
<li>Whiplash</li>
<li>Molly&#39;s Game</li>
<li>Pride</li>
<li>Greenland</li>

</ul>
<h2>Podcasts</h2>
<ul>
<li>Daily Tech News Show</li>
<li>Tech&#39;s Message</li>
<li>Kermode and Mayo&#39;s Film Review</li>
<li>More or Less: Behind the Stats</li>
<li>Full Fact</li>

</ul>
<h2>TV Shows</h2>
<ul>
<li>The Expanse</li>
<li>Arcane</li>
<li>Bosch</li>
<li>Star Trek: Voyager</li>
<li>Mare of Easttown</li>
<li>Ted Lasso</li>
<li>Squid Game</li>
<li>Invincible</li>
<li>Catastrophe</li>
<li>Foundation</li>

</ul>
<h2>Books (books I rated 5 stars on Goodreads)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Project Hail Mary </li>
<li>Shadows of the Fall (Shadow of Terra, #2)</li>
<li>Fundamentals of Data Visualization: A Primer on Making Informative and Compelling Figures</li>
<li>The Visual Display of Quantitative Information</li>
<li>Exile (Trilogy)</li>
<li>Heaven&#39;s River (Bobiverse, #4)</li>
<li>Flight of the Javelin (Trilogy)</li>
<li>Asylum</li>
<li>Saga (Trilogy)</li>
<li>House of Suns</li>
<li>The Divide (2 books)</li>
<li>The Code (2 books)</li>
<li>The Palladium Wars (Trilogy)</li>

</ul>

</body>

]]>            </description>
        </item>


        <!-- Why every Product Manager should build a website -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article9</guid>
            <title>Why every Product Manager should build a website</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/why-every-product-manager-should-build-a-website.html</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 17:00:00 BST</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[
<body>
  <main class="page">
    <!-- set title, pubdate, and article style -->
<header class="header">
<nav>
<a href="../index.html">Home</a></p>
</nav>
<h1>Why every Product Manager should build a website</h1>
<div class="metarow">
<div class="pubdate">
<p><time datetime="2021-04-18">18 Apr 2021</time> · Mark Evans</p>
</div>
<div class="articlestyle">
<p>Article Style: page, clean, sans serif, a dash of blue</p>
</div>
</div>
</header>
<header style="clear: both"></header>

<!-- main article -->
<article class="article">

<!-- Intro - section -->
<section>
<p>I&#39;ve used very specific wording in the title of this post. The key word in the title is
          <strong>build</strong>, I specifically don&#39;t state that every product manager should have a website, or
          write a blog, I don&#39;t even think it&#39;s that important if Product Managers actually publish the
          website&#39;s they build, but I do believe that all Product Managers (ok, not all, only those who are
          responsible for online products) should go through the process of building a website. Why? well, like many of
          my suggestions, it all comes back to Ben Franklin (<a href='https://quoteinvestigator.com/2019/02/27/tell/' target=”_blank”>or
            maybe Confucius</a>) and the following quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Tell me, and I will listen; Teach me, and I’ll remember; Involve me, and I will learn.”
            — Benjamin Franklin</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The reason I like this quote so much, (and refer to it so often) is because I really believe it. It&#39;s the
          reason this website exists, I wanted to learn HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. I didn&#39;t start with a book or a
          course...I started by building a page. This meant I made a lot of mistakes initially, mistakes I wouldn&#39;t
          have made if I&#39;d started with a book, but I find that mistakes are hard to forget, whereas it&#39;s easy
          to forget some instructions in a book that tell you how something should be done.</p>
<p>OK, but what does this have to do Product Managers building websites? To help answer this question, I&#39;d
          propose a small tweak to the above quote i.e.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Tell me, and I will listen; Teach me, and I’ll remember; Involve me, and I will understand and
            appreciate.”
            — Mark Evans</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Learning something new is great, and I&#39;ve really enjoyed learning how to build this website, but,
          it&#39;s also had a couple of side effects:</p>
<ol>
<li>I have a much better <strong>understanding</strong> of what my development team does.</li>
<li>I have a much better <strong>appreciation</strong> for what my development team does.</li>

</ol>
<p>Before I go any further, let me make one thing clear, <strong>I am not in any way comparing my tiny blog to
            the products that my developers build</strong>. This website, and the products I manage, are so far apart in
          scale and complexity that it would be laughable to even attempt to compare the two.</p>
</section>

<section>
<h2>Understanding & Appreciation</h2>
<p>Without a data team (to source, qualify, cleanse etc.) and a development team (to build the tools that allow
          users to easily access the data) my role would be utterly redundant, I&#39;d literally have no products to
          manage, sales would have no products to sell, and marketing would have no products to promote. So, I&#39;ve
          always had a strong sense of appreciation for both of these teams. But, building my little hand crafted
          website (with just HTML and CSS...so no actual programming) over the last few months has only increased my
          appreciation for what my developers do. Even my meagre website, with its 7 pages has required quite a lot of
          effort to create and maintain. For example, I&#39;ve:</p>
<ul>
<li>Moved from using CodePen to VSCode.</li>
<li>Gone through a retagging exercise to ensure that article specific HTML5 tags are used e.g.
            &lt;article&gt;, &lt;section&gt; etc..</li>
<li>Refactored the website&#39;s folder structure, as I realised my initial structure wasn&#39;t scalable.
          </li>
<li>Moved the source files from my local PC to GitHub.</li>
<li>Updated my version of Git due to a recent security vulnerability.</li>

</ul>
<p>The important thing to note about the list above, is that <strong>none of that effort has resulted in any
            changes that are visible to someone visiting the website</strong>. Now, if all that has been required for my
          little website, imagine the size and quantity of &quot;unseen&quot; tasks that are required for a global data
          product built with numerous dependencies, strict security and privacy requirements, multiple databases,
          complex access and entitlement systems, and multiple frameworks etc.</p>
<p>So, stop reading about building websites, and pop over to CodePen and start building one &#128522;.</p>
</section>

<!-- feedback - section -->
<section>
<p>
          If you have any comments on this article then please get in touch via Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/dbs_sticky" target="_blank">@dbs_sticky</a>).
        </p>
</section>
</article>
</main>
</body>

]]>            </description>
        </item>



        <!-- Rowing tips after 15 m meters -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article8</guid>
            <title>My indoor rowing tips after 15 million meters</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/my-rowing-tips-after-15-million-meters.html</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 9 Apr 2021 16:00:00 BST</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[
<body>
    <main class="page">
        <!-- set title, pubdate, and article style -->
<header class="header">
<nav>
<a href="../index.html">Home</a></p>
</nav>
<h1>My indoor rowing tips after 15 million meters</h1>
<div class="metarow">
<div class="pubdate">
<p><time datetime="2021-04-09">9 Apr 2021</time> · Mark Evans</p>
</div>
<div class="articlestyle">
<p>Article Style: page, clean, sans serif</p>
</div>
</div>
</header>
<header style="clear: both"></header>

<!-- main article -->
<article class="article">

<!-- Intro - section -->
<section>
<h2>Background</h2>
<p>I bought my <a href='https://www.concept2.com/service/indoor-rowers/model-c'>Concept 2 Model C</a>
                    rower
                    in 2001, my plan (like most people who buy exercise equipment) was to use it every week. And, like
                    most
                    people, I failed. I used the rower sporadically for a while, and then I moved house, and it just sat
                    there in my new home, gathering dust. I'd get the urge to start using it again (yes...January) and
                    as usual, it didn't last. I've always done some form of exercise, either in the gym or running,
                    and have had some long periods of running every week, but I don't think I've ever exercised
                    consistently every week for a period longer than a year.</p>
</section>

<section>
<h2>2014 - New Year's day</h2>
<p>This all changed when I hit 40. My daily routine was basically, driving to work, sitting at my desk
                    for 8hrs, driving home, making the family dinner, and then sitting in front of the TV with the wife
                    for an hour or so before bed. This was not exactly an active lifestyle. So I made a New Year's
                    resolution to row at least 30km every week (4x5km, 1x10km). I used Excel and made a big table where
                    each row was a week, and each column was 5km (it had 10 columns, so 50km). I printed the table on A3
                    paper, and stuck it up on the wall in the garage right next to the rowing machine. The aim was
                    simple, "don't break the streak", the longer I could hit 30km each week, the less
                    likely I would be to miss a week, because I'd "break the streak". I had to start off
                    slowly, but by week 3 I was up to 30km, and with the exception of a few weeks (house move, and a
                    work trip to NYC) I hit my target.</p>
<P>The table was not the thing that kept me going, 30km per week
                    on the rower meant about 2 1/4 hrs of my time, and just rowing can be boring. To help alleviate the
                    boredom I attached my iPad to the rower, got some sports headphones, and started watching Star Trek
                    (original) from the very beginning. <strong>Exercise time was now also Star Trek time!</strong>.
                    When I got to the end of Star Trek, I watched Stargate SG1, all 10 seasons, and then Atlantis, and
                    then...you get the idea. I watched TV that I would look forward to. During September I hit 1,000,000
                    meters, and as I'd been logging my rows in the Concept 2 online log book, I qualified for my
                    free 1 million meter t-shirt and badge.</p>
<p>Here's an image of the initial simple setup:</p>
<p><img src="../images/rower2014.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"></p>
<p>And here's the chart for my first year:</p>
<p><img src="../images/rowing-log.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"></p>
</section>

<section>
<h2>2015</h2>
<p>2015 carried on much like 2014, 30km per week (this time I didn't miss any weeks). I hit 2 million
                    meters in May (you don't get any freebies for 2 million) and I also rowed my first 20km. I did my
                    first 1/2 Marathon in July, and then my 2nd in December, when I also hit 3 million meters.</p>
</section>

<section>
<h2>2016 - This is the year when I realised I had been lazy</h2>
<p>There were three things that happened in 2016 that made me realise that I needed to up my game:</p>
<ol>
<li>I set a New Year's resolution to row a Marathon by the end of the year.</li>
<li>I read <a href='https://www.amazon.co.uk/Daily-Breathe-Deeper-Live-Better/dp/0595434371'>Row
                            Daily, Breathe Deeper, Live Better: A Guide to Moderate Exercise.</a></li>
<li>A friend of mine casually mentioned that she swam for an hour each day.</li>

</ol>
<p>2016 started well, with my 3rd 1/2 Marathon in January, but by week 6 my long running streak was
                    broken due to a case of "man-flu" that lasted more than 2 weeks. There followed another
                    couple of 1/2 Marathons during the year. But, it was points 2) and 3) that eventually led me to
                    reassess my rowing goal of 30km per week, and this happened in August.</p>
<p>I was already doing a lot of what was discussed in "Row Daily, Breathe Deeper, Live Better: A
                    Guide to Moderate Exercise", but it was only when I got to the chapter on case studies that it
                    suddenly occurred to me that the book was targeted at old people (ok, at this time I was 43...but I
                    mean really old people, as in 60+). All the case studies were of people in their 60s and 70s.
                    <strong>So, here was me thinking that my 30km per week was pretty good, and here's this book
                        encouraging people in their 70s to row 70km per week!</strong> Combined with my friend doing an
                    hour swim every day, I realised that it was time to up my game. So, during August I set a new goal
                    of 70km per week (typically 7x10km). I rowed my first Marathon in November (3hr12m53.6s,
                    2:17/500m,), and hit 5 million meters in the first week of January (finally...a new t-shirt and
                    badge).</p>
</section>

<section>
<h2>Setting challenges - 100km in a day</h2>
<p>Each year I try and set a new rowing challenge, this is typically something like "row a Marathon this year", or "beat my 10km time", but during 2017 I set myself the challenge of rowing 100km in a day, I started around 8am and rowed 10km, then had a 30min break, followed by another 10km, and so on, unfortunately after 80km I had some serious knee pain, so had to stop.</p>
<p>During late 2020 I was approaching the 15 million meter mark, so decided to attempt the '100km in a day' challenge again, but I timed it such that I'd hit the 15 million meters during the 100km attempt. I started around 8am, finished around 11pm, and spent around 9hrs on the rower in total. This time there were no knee issues, <strong>I'd done it! and I swore to never do it again</strong>, it was probably the hardest physical activity I'd ever done. Rowing 10x10km in a day requires similar effort to running 10x10km in a day (ok, maybe about 80% when compared to running). Note: Two ladies in France each managed to row <a href='https://www.row2k.com/features/899/100k-A-Day-Keeps-The-Doctor-Away/'>100km per day, every day, for a month!</a> That's more than 3 million meters in a month (it typically takes me around 2 years to row 3 million meters). When setting goals, don't worry about what other people are doing (it's a big world with a lot of talented people), if you do it will only demotivate you. Your goals should be personal to you.</p>
</section>

<section>
<h2>Concept 2 setup, maintenance, and upgrades</h2>
<p>My rowing setup has evolved over the years to the point where I'm quite happy with the current configuration, which includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>A dedicated wall mounted TV</li>
<li>An Ethernet connected Amazon Fire TV stick (you don't want to be dealing with Wi-Fi issues 1/2 way through your row)</li>
<li>An Amazon Echo (for audio and voice control of the TV).</li>
<li>A wall chart for marking off each row.</li>

</ul>
<p>Here's the current setup:</p>
<p><img src="../images/rower2021.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"></p>
<p>At the end of this Summer (2021) my Concept 2 will be 20 years old. Concept 2s are built to survive the harsh environment of commercial gyms, if you buy one for home use, they should last forever and require very little maintenance (they also hold their value well, during the pandemic my rower was still worth about 80% of what I paid for it!). Most of the changes I've made to mine have not actually been required, here's how I've maintained and upgraded it over the last 20 years:</p>
<ul>
<li>After each row, I clean the main rail with glass cleaner (as the seat rollers collect gunk).</li>
<li>Every month I oil the chain, nothing fancy, just some basic 3-in-1.</li>
<li>Every year I give the main flywheel enclosure a vac to get rid of the dust.</li>
<li>Every year or so I replace the batteries in the Performance Monitor (PM). Not because they are flat, but to reduce the chance of them leaking and killing the PM.</li>
<li>Every 3 million meters or so I replace the seat rollers, they cost around £28.</li>
<li>I upgraded the handle from the original Model C version to the version that ships with the Model D and E. There was nothing wrong with the original handle, I just wanted to use the latest version.</li>
<li>I upgraded the PM from the PM2+ that it originally came with, to the latest PM5. Again, this was not really necessary as the PM2+ was working just fine, but, I wanted to link the PM to a phone, so I could automatically log all my rows with the Concept 2 online logbook (I'd been adding them manually up to this point). The PM5 is quite expensive (£155), but, I got £90 for my PM2+ on eBay, so the upgrade only set me back £65.</li>
<li>I few years ago I bought a replacement bungie cord (the part that pulls back on the handle), but I've not got around to fitting it yet.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section>
<h2>My tips for anyone who's new to indoor rowing</h2>
<ul>
<li>There's nothing harder than getting home from work, and then dragging your arse back out again to go to a gym. <strong>If you can, buy a rower</strong>, Concept 2s hold their value really well, if it turns out that rowing is not for you, just sell it.</li>
<li>Set a goal, print out a table/chart, and mark off each row, <strong>start a streak</strong>, and try to keep it going.</li>
<li>Attach a tablet to the rower, or set up a TV and watch some sci-fi (other genres are acceptable), or listen to podcasts or audio books, but <strong>do something that will keep your mind occupied</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Put some padding on the seat</strong>, those things are not meant for long rows!</li>
<li><strong>Log your rows with the Concept 2 Logbook</strong>, the rewards might not be much, but I wear my t-shirt with pride.</li>
<li><a href='https://www.c2forum.com/'>Sign up to the Concept 2 forum</a>, it's a good place to get answers to any rowing or Concept 2 related questions.</li>

</ul>
</section>

<section>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Rowing is now part of my lifestyle, it's fully integrated into my <a href='../posts/anatomy-of-a-lockdown-day.html'>daily routine</a>. I'm not trying to break records (obviously, I'm watching TV at the same time), but I am trying to make up for the 8hrs a day I spend sitting at a desk, and to be honest, 10km per day is probably only just managing that.</p>
</section>

<!-- feedback - section -->
<section>
<p>
                    If you have any comments on this article then please get in touch via Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/dbs_sticky" target="_blank">@dbs_sticky</a>).
                </p>
</section>
</article>
</main>
</body>

]]>            </description>
        </item>


        <!-- chart picker -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article7</guid>
            <title>Chart Picker</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/chart-picker.html</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 11:00:00 BST</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[
<body>
    <main class="page">
    <!-- set title, pubdate, and article style -->
<header class="header">
<nav>
<a href="../index.html">Home</a></p>
</nav>
<h1>Chart Picker</h1>
<div class="metarow">
<div class="pubdate"><p><time datetime="2021-03-28">28 Mar 2021</time> · Mark Evans</p></div>
<div class="articlestyle"><p>Article Style: page, clean, sans serif</p></div>
</div>
</header>
<header style="clear: both"></header>

<!-- main article -->
<article class="article">

<!-- Intro - section -->
<section>
<h2>Background</h2>
<p>Whether you work in data science, data analytics, finance, strategy, user experience, sales, marketing, or product, at some point you will be creating data visualisations, either for use externally (in your products and on social media), or internally (in your presentations and reports). As an employee of an information and analytics company, it’s important that the visualisations I choose reflect the same high standard as the underlying data, or at the very least, don’t misrepresent the data.</p>
<p>As a product manager, I’ve used a variety of tools over the years to create mock-ups. Some tools output high-fidelity designs, but typically I’m dealing with high-level concepts that need to be created quickly and updated often (based on user feedback). For these scenarios, I’ve recently started using a free and open-source tool called <a href='https://excalidraw.com/' target="_blank">Excalidraw</a> (see my blog post about <a href='../posts/drawing-with-excalidraw.html' target="_blank">Drawing with Excalidraw</a>).</p>
<p>During early 2021 I was managing the rebuild of one of my company&#39;s analytics tools, and the new version required the extensive use of charts in order to visualise a wide variety of data, as usual, I turned to Excalidraw to create the initial mock-ups. Before I knew it, I had amassed a large number of basic chart types, so I turned these into an Excalidraw library and added my library to the project in <a href='https://github.com/excalidraw/excalidraw-libraries' target="_blank">GitHub</a>. You can download my library <a href='https://libraries.excalidraw.com/?sort=default#dbssticky-data-viz' target="_blank">here</a> (title: &#39;Data Viz&#39;, author: &#39;@dbs-sticky&#39;).</p>
<p>I then decided to take my library of charts and generate a “chart picker” diagram. I based this off an existing concept developed by Dr. Andrew Abela from <a href='https://extremepresentation.com/' target="_blank">ExtremePresentations</a> (anyone interested in charting is probably already familiar with this <a href='https://extremepresentation.com/design/7-charts/' target="_blank">classic version</a>). I made some changes to Dr. Abela&#39;s design, mostly around the Distribution section which I have expanded with more options. My diagram is designed to help you choose a chart based on your data, and what you are trying to convey to the user. My initial aim for creating this chart picker was to share it with my colleagues, I&#39;ve since shared it publicly, and have now made it available on <a href='https://github.com/dbs-sticky/ChartPicker' target="_blank">GitHub</a> for anyone to use or to improve upon.</p>

</section>

<!-- mid - section -->
<section>
<h2>Chart Picker links</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href='../images/chart-picker-compressed.png' target="_blank">View\download the chart picker as a .png</a></li>
<li><a href='../images/chart-picker-compressed.svg' target="_blank">View\download the chart picker as a .svg</a></li>
<li><a href='https://t.co/swXFJLvAwM' target="_blank">View\edit your own instance of the chart picker at Excalidraw</a></li>
<li><a href='https://github.com/dbs-sticky/ChartPicker' target="_blank">Follow\contribute to the chart picker project at GitHub</a></li>

</ul>

</section>

<!-- Conclusion - section -->
<section>
<h2>Chart Picker screenshot</h2>
<p>This is a zoomed in view of the distribution section of the chart picker.</p>
<img src="../images/chart-picker-snippet.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" alt="A snippet of the 'Chart Picker'">
</section>

<!-- feedback - section -->
<section>
<p>
                If you have any comments on this article then please get in touch via Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/dbs_sticky" target="_blank">@dbs_sticky</a>).
            </p>
</section>

</article>
</main>
</body>

]]>            </description>
        </item>



        <!-- rss part 1 -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article6</guid>
            <title>What is RSS and what are 'aggregators'?</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/rss-part-1.html</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 7 Mar 2021 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[
      <body>
    <main class="page">
    <!-- set title, pubdate, and article style -->
<header class="header">
<nav>
<a href="index.html">Home</a></p>
</nav>
<h1>RSS Part 1:<br>What is RSS and what are 'aggregators'?</h1>
<p class="pubdate">
<p class="pubdate"><time datetime="2021-03-07">7 Mar 2021</time> · Mark Evans</p>
<p class="articlestyle">Article Style: page, wide, clean, sans serif</p>
</header>
<header style="clear: both"></header>

<!-- main article -->
<article class="article">

<!-- Intro - section -->
<section>
<h2>What is RSS?</h2>
<p>RSS (Really Simple Syndication) is a web feed that allows users and applications to access updates to
                websites in a standardised, computer-readable format. These feeds can, for example, allow you to keep
                track of many (potentially, hundreds) different websites in a single news aggregator.</p>
<p>Below you can see an example of the contents of an RSS feed. It&#39;s simply a channel (e.g. your
                favourite news site), followed by a list of articles. Users of RSS never actually look at the feed (in
                the same way that you never see all the metadata associated with each e-mail you receive), it&#39;s not
                meant for people, it&#39;s meant for machines, i.e. the RSS aggregators.</p>
<pre><code>
&lt;channel&gt;
&lt;title&gt;OnlyRSS&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;link&gt;https://onlyrss.org&lt;/link&gt;
&lt;description&gt;The latest posts from OnlyRSS.org&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Drawing with Excalidraw&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;link&gt;https://onlyrss.org/drawing-with-excalidraw&lt;/link&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;Excalidraw is described by its creators...&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Working from home hardware&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;link&gt;https://onlyrss.org/working-from-home-hardware&lt;/link&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;I recently wrote about my weekday lockdown...&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/item&gt;
&lt;/channel&gt;
</code></pre>
</section>

<!-- RSS aggregators - section -->
<section>
<h2>RSS aggregators</h2>
<p><strong>An RSS aggregator is similar to an e-mail client, but rather than e-mails, it aggregates articles.</strong> And
                like e-mail applications, some RSS aggregators are desktop apps, and others are online applications. <a href='https://feedly.com/' target="_blank">Feedly</a> and <a href='https://www.inoreader.com/' target="_blank">Inoreader</a> are two
                popular online versions and both have similar capabilities.</p>
<p>Here&#39;s how the example above could appear in an RSS aggregator. It doesn&#39;t have to appear like
                this, for example, you could choose to view a list of just the titles, or you could select to step
                through each article in turn (no different to the options you would get in any decent e-mail client).
                <img src="images/rss-for-productivity-1.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
</p>
</section>

<!-- It's not just articles - section -->
<section>
<h3>It's not just articles</h3>
<p>For simplicity, so far I&#39;ve only discussed articles, but RSS aggregators can do more than just show
                you the latest news. Below is a list of the various types of content that you can aggregate:</p>
<ul>
<li>Articles</li>
<li>Blog posts</li>
<li>Forum posts</li>
<li>Videos e.g. YouTube</li>
<li>Keyword search alerts e.g. Google\Bing etc.</li>
<li>Newsletters</li>
<li>Daily weather reports</li>
<li>Podcasts</li>
<li>Updates to documents e.g. Wikipedia, Confluence etc.</li>
<li>Status changes e.g. parcel tracking, Jira tickets etc.</li>
<li>Price alerts e.g. CamelCamelCamel etc.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<!-- and it's not just aggregation - section -->
<section>
<h3>...and it's not just aggregation</h3>
<p>The basic requirement of an RSS aggregator is that it aggregates content via RSS feeds. But, much like
                e-mail clients, RSS aggregators tend to offer more than just this basic capability. In addition to
                aggregating content, RSS aggregators can offer other benefits, e.g.:</p>
<ul>
<li>Searching for feeds (so you don&#39;t have to hunt down the feed at the source website)</li>
<li>Keyword search results e.g. allowing you to see all new Google results for a keyword search</li>
<li>Deduplication i.e. remove or bundle together articles with similar content</li>
<li>Prioritise content e.g. highlight all content that includes a certain keyword, or from a specific
                    source.</li>
<li>Mute content e.g. hide all content that contains a certain keyword or phrase like &quot;Game of
                    Thrones finale&quot;</li>
<li>Store all read content and index for search</li>
<li>Tag content to be &#39;read later&#39;</li>
<li>Tag content as &#39;favourite&#39;</li>
<li>Group content into folders, or apply categories e.g. UX, DataViz, etc.</li>
<li>Highlight sections of content and add notes</li>
<li>Share content e.g. directly to social networks, as an e-mail newsletter, or even an RSS feed!</li>
</ul>
</section>

<!-- Summary - section -->
<section>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>Hopefully I&#39;ve managed to explain what RSS is, and also to convey some of the benefits of using an RSS
            aggregator. My original plan for this article was to also describe in detail how I use an RSS aggregator
            (specifically Feedly) to keep on top of my various interests, but I didn&#39;t want anyone reading this
            article to be overwhelmed and to lose sight of the one key takeaway i.e. <strong>RSS is a powerful tool for
                keeping on top of online content, and keeping your knowledge up to date</strong>.</p>
</section>

<!-- feedback - section -->
<section>
<p>
                If you have any comments on this article then please get in touch via Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/dbs_sticky" target="_blank">@dbs_sticky</a>).
            </p>
</section>
</article>
</main>
</body>

]]>            </description>
        </item>


        <!-- drawing with Excalidraw -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article5</guid>
            <title>Drawing with Excalidraw</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/drawing-with-excalidraw.html</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 3 Mar 2021 20:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[

   <!-- set title, pubdate, and article style -->
<header class="header">
<nav>
<a href="index.html">Home</a></p>
</nav>
<h1>Drawing with Excalidraw</h1>
<p class="pubdate">
<p class="pubdate"><time datetime="2021-03-02">2 Mar 2021</time> · Mark Evans</p>
<p class="articlestyle">Article Style: Excalidraw</p>
</header>
<header style="clear: both"></header>

<!-- main article -->
<article class="article">

<!-- Intro - section -->
<section>
<h2>Excaliwhatnow?</h2>
<p>Excalidraw is described by its creators as a "Virtual whiteboard for sketching hand-drawn like diagrams".
                I'd describe it slightly differently, I think I'd go with "a drawing tool that's so easy to use that you
                spend your time making sure the drawing is effective, rather than 'pixel-fiddling'".
            </p>
<p>Excalidraw is great for quickly creating diagrams (you can see lots of great examples on the bottom of <a target="blank" href="https://blog.excalidraw.com/one-year-of-excalidraw/">this page</a>),
                but it can be used for "sketch" style drawings, like the drawing below of my rowing setup.</p>

<img src="/images/drawing-with-excalidraw-1.png">
<p><a href="/images/drawing-with-excalidraw-1.svg" target="_blank">click to view full size</a></p>

<p>Some of Excalidraw's features:
    <ul>
<li>runs in the browser</li>
<li>supports real-time collaboration</li>
<li>supports multiple export formats</li>
<li>is secure (end-to-end encrypted)</li>
<li>is vector based (so scales to all sizes)</li>
<li>is very easy to learn (no "learning" required)</li>
<li>is open source</li>
<li>is free to use</li>

</ul>
</p>
</section>

<!-- How I use it -->
<section>
<h2>How I use it</h2>
<p>As a Product Manager, I'm often having to define what apps look like, how they're structured, what
                components they include etc. and I used to do this using hi-fidelity mock-up tools such as AxureRP (or
                even Adobe illustrator!). And to be honest, I wasted a lot of time obsessing over the size, colour and
                exact location of various page components. Once my company got serious about UX and started embedding
                dedicated UX resource within our squads, then it was no longer my responsibility to make my mock-ups
                pixel perfect.</p>
<p> This is where Excalidraw really shines (it's hard to be pixel perfect when there are no straight
                lines!), as its focus is on a "hand-drawn" aesthetic, it lends itself well towards the creation of
                "quick-and-dirty" sketches where the focus is to portray an idea or concept, rather than to represent a
                final pixel perfect design. Sketches can be created and altered quickly, and all from within a browser
                (important for those of us who work for large corporations and don't have the admin rights required to
                 install apps on our PCs).</p>
<p>The mock-up below of a news search page took about 15mins to produce, but the sketch does highlight quite a few important features about the search page concept.</p>

<img src="/images/drawing-with-excalidraw-2.png">
<p><a href="/images/drawing-with-excalidraw-2.svg" target="_blank">click to view full size</a></p>
<p> In addition to using it at work for mock-ups, it's also my "go-to" drawing app for this blog, as you can see in my post about my <a href="anatomy-of-a-lockdown-day.html"> lockdown days</a>.</p>
</section>

<!-- Libraries - section -->
<section>
<h2>Libraries make creating diagrams even quicker</h2>
<p>As I've mentioned, one of the benefits of Excalidarw is the speed, but the existinace of a small (but
                growing) community of users who share their <a href="https://libraries.excalidraw.com/" target="_blank">Libraries</a>
                makes it even faster to create diagrams.</p>
<img src="images/drawing-with-excalidraw-3.png">
</section>


<!-- Conclusion - section -->
<section>
<h2>Conclusions</h2>
<p>I really can't recommend Excalidraw strongly enough, it's a great tool, built and maintained by a group of enthusiastic developers who are actively engaging with their users. But, the only way to see how good it really is, is to  <a href="https://excalidraw.com/">go and sketch something :-)</a></p>

</section>
<!-- feedback - section -->
<section>
<p>
          If you have any comments on this article, then please reply to the tweet below:</a>
</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Here&#39;s a short blog post about the fast, secure, and extremely easy to use drawing tool, Excalidraw. <a href="https://t.co/NRxxHSmDs9">https://t.co/NRxxHSmDs9</a></p>&mdash; Mark R Evans (@dbs_sticky) <a href="https://twitter.com/dbs_sticky/status/1366838969003085826?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 2, 2021</a></blockquote><script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</section>

</article>

]]>            </description>
        </item>

        <!-- Working from home hardware -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article4</guid>
            <title>Working from home hardware</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/working-from-home-hardware.html</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[

 <div class="header"><h1>Working from home hardware </h1><p class="pubdate"> 18 Feb 2021 · Mark Evans</p><p class="articlestyle"> Article Style: Large, Clean, Serif</p></div><div style="clear: both;"></div><div class="article"><p> I recently wrote about my <a href="anatomy-of-a-lockdown-day.html"> weekday lockdown routine</a>. In this article I'll be describing the hardware I use to do my job while working from home. As a Product Manager for a suite of News and Data Analytics products, I use the tools that most office workers are familiar with, i.e. Office 365 apps, but I'm also often sketching UIs, writing requirements in Confluence, or using tools such as PowerBI etc. to analyse and visualise large datasets.</p><p> My PC is located in a bay window at one end of my kitchen diner, it's used by the whole family, and is always on. When I'm working from home I use my work laptop via a docking station and a keyboard\mouse switch, switching between work and home computers only requires the push of a couple of buttons.</p><h2>The setup</h2><p>Here&#39;s my WFH components:</p><ul><li>2 x Dell U2715H monitors (27&quot; 2560x1440)</li><li>Logitech C920 HD webcam</li><li>Logitech MX Master mouse</li><li>TerraMaster F2-421 NAS (2x4GB raid 1)</li><li>Keychron K2 keyboard (with Red switches)</li><li>Ikea Bekant desk (160x80cm)</li><li>Dell D6000 Universal dock*</li><li>Dell Latitude 7490 laptop*</li><li>Plantronics C520 headset*</li></ul><p><em>*provided by employer</em></p><p>The setup is connected to a 300Mbps (down) and 40Mbps (up) Broadband connection <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G.fast">(g.fast)</a> via Gigabit Ethernet.</p><p><img src="images/article4figure1.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" alt="article4figure1"></p><h2>Outputs</h2><h3>Monitors</h3><p>If you are using a laptop when WFH and have NOT got it connected to an external monitor, for the love of God please just stop right now, go on Amazon, buy a new monitor (or two) and do not return to your laptop until after the new monitor arrives. There are lots of good ways to save money in life, not buying a decent monitor is not one of them! <strong>You are staring at your monitor for more than 8hrs a day, this is not a component where you want to cut corners and &#39;make-do&#39;</strong>. Your employer should provide you with a suitable monitor, or reimburse you if you buy your own. If your employer does not believe a good monitor is worthwhile, then hold off on ordering a new monitor from Amazon, as your highest priority is finding a new employer.</p><p>When deciding which monitor to choose, I&#39;d suggest that anything with a resolution of 2560x1440px. A width of 2560px means you can have 2 apps of 1280px side-by-side, and most apps run well at 1280px. Your laptop display can be reserved for your more &quot;reference&quot; style apps, e.g. calendar, chat application, etc., while your main display is reserved for the apps required for your current task.</p><h3>Speakers</h3><p>My family don't need to hear what others are saying during my conference calls, so I use a wired headset. I know many people use Bluetooth headphones, and as good as modern Bluetooth is, I still find it less hassle to use a wire (wired headphones don't suddenly decide to connect to other devices when you're about to join a conference call).</p><h2>Inputs</h2><h3>Mice</h3><p>Again, not a component where you want to make compromises. <strong>I&#39;d recommend any of the Logitech mice in the <a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-gb/mx/master-series.html">MX Master series</a></strong>. They&#39;re geared towards productivity, and include enough useful features to make them good value for money. You don&#39;t have to get the latest version (the MX Master 3 retails for almost £100), the original version is often heavily discounted and sometimes dips below £50 <a href="https://uk.camelcamelcamel.com/product/B00ULNAOMA">(view price history)</a>.</p><h3>Keyboard</h3><p>Whereas the benefit of a good monitor and mouse are clear, the return on investment of a good quality keyboard is less clear. Keyboards come in 2 main flavours:</p><ol><li>The &#39;rubber dome&#39; keyboards that you&#39;ll find on almost all office desks across the World, and the</li><li>&#39;mechanical&#39; keyboards that you&#39;ll find on the desk of any discerning journalist, developer, or gamer.*</li></ol><p><em>*and maybe on the desks of very discerning Product Managers :-)</em></p><p>&#39;Mechanical&#39; and &#39;rubber dome&#39; here refer to the type of switches used for each key to register the key&#39;s actuation. You can buy a good &#39;rubber dome&#39; keyboard for less than £20. To get a good mechanical keyboard you&#39;re looking at at least £50, with serious mechanical keyboard enthusiasts (yes, it&#39;s a whole thing) spending £100+ on the keyboard itself, and then another £50+ on the keycaps (yes, that&#39;s also a whole thing). I have a mechanical keyboard on my desk, but I&#39;m not recommending anyone goes out and buys a mechanical keyboard. I&#39;d definitely put this component in the &#39;nice to have&#39; bucket.</p><h3>Webcam</h3><p>My wife and I both have the Logitech C920, this has been the &#39;go to&#39; HD webcam for streamers for many years now. When I bought mine back in 2018 I paid just £35...today they cost closer to £100. You can see how the price has changed for this particular webcam since February 2020.</p><p><img src="/images/article4figure2.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" alt="article4image2"></p><p>Before spending money on a price inflated HD webcam, the first thing to try is to improve your lighting. <strong>There&#39;s no point having a good quality camera if you have a south facing window directly behind you</strong>. Shut the blinds, and pick up some LED lighting that can be mounted on top of the monitor. Maybe then consider a good webcam (after supply has caught up with demand).</p><h3>Microphone</h3><p>As I mentioned above, I use a headset, and it's not just becasue of Bluetooth issues. The best way to avoid background noise during conference calls is to use a dedicated headset with a mic, the mic is located right next to your mouth, and is unlikely to pick up other sounds from within your home. Bluetooth ear buds are great when you're out and about, or going for a run, and they are OK for the occasional call, but, if you are working from home on a regular basis, then you don't need to compromise. Get a dedicated wired headset, the other people on your call will thank you.</p><h2>Other</h2><h3>Ethernet</h3><p>I was lucky enough to wire up the house with Ethernet (CAT6) in January 2020, just before the whole COVID-19 thing kicked off. At home I have number of bandwidth hungry stationary devices i.e. 3 TVs, 2 desktop PCs, and a NAS. I also have a laptop (permanently on a desk), a Chromebook (that get&#39;s moved around a lot) and a very large number of IoT devices. As good as modern Wi-Fi is, it just doesn&#39;t have the same level of consistency that you get from Ethernet cable, and when you have 4 people potentially all on video calls at the same time, consistency is what you want. <strong>If it is at all practical, I would strongly recommend wiring up your home for Ethernet</strong>.</p><h2>Conclusions</h2><p>I realise that my setup might be considered &#39;overkill&#39;, but my thinking is simple, I&#39;m spending &gt;8hrs per day sitting at that desk, staring at those screens, tapping on that keyboard and shifting around that mouse, therefore it&#39;s worth putting some thought (and some money) into those components.</p></div>

]]>            </description>
        </item>        <!-- Anatomy of a lockdown weekday -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article3</guid>
            <title>Anatomy of a lockdown weekday</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/anatomy-of-a-lockdown-day.html</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 15:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[

<h2>Prior to lockdown</h2><p>Prior to lockdown, I used to work from 4 different locations:</p><ul><li>Bishopsgate (round trip commute ≈ 3hrs, car, train, tube, walk)</li><li>Heathrow (round trip commute ≈ 2hrs, car)</li><li>Sutton (round trip commute ≈ 2.5-3.5hrs, car)</li><li>Home (0hrs)</li></ul><p>My start time each day was dependent upon which office I was working from, the earliest being when I was working from Sutton. To avoid the M25 traffic, I&#39;d wake at 5:30am, leave home at 5:50am and arrive at the office around 7am.</p><p>During a typical week, I was spending around <strong>11hrs simply travelling to and from my place of work</strong>. And when I arrived at work, I was typically sitting at a desk in front of a laptop.....a laptop that I&#39;d just carried with me from home.</p><p>In a typical week I&#39;d work from each of the 4 locations at least once, so there was no real sense of a fixed routine.</p><h2>During lockdown</h2><p>During March 2020, when all employees in the UK were asked to work from home (if practical), this all changed. Being a Product Manager who was often in a different location as the teams I needed to work with e.g. Tech, Sales, Marketing, Data Science, Data engineering, etc., I was used to &quot;remote working&quot;, even when that meant being in one office, and connecting with teams in a different office.</p><p>I&#39;d also got into the habit of working from home at least once a week (usually when I had to focus on a task). So shifting to working from home full-time was not a big deal, and in many ways it was preferable (for a start, I was saving 11hrs by not travelling).</p><h3>A new routine</h3><p>After a few months of working from home, I&#39;d found that my weekdays had settled into a repeating pattern that included: reading, working, eating, exercise, and TV. This is shown in the sketch below:</p><p><img src="/images/article3figure1.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" alt="article3figure1"></p><p>I&#39;d start the day by getting up around 7am (I struggle to sleep past 6am to be honest) and would read my Kindle for around an hour, then I&#39;d start work around 8:30am. First thing I would do is check the news from the previous night via Feedly (I subscribe to around 120 feeds). I&#39;d often have a small lunch at 11:30am while at my desk, and then I&#39;d either go for a 5km run or walk at midday (while listening to podcasts). Right after my lunch\exercise break I&#39;d check Feedly again, and then get back to work. At the end of the workday (around 5pm) I&#39;d check Feedly one last time, and then I&#39;d be thinking about what to cook the family for dinner (we eat at 6pm, which I guess is earlier than most). </p><p>After dinner I&#39;d read again, and then it would be time for my second exercise session of the day, typically a 10km row on the Concept 2 which I&#39;d combine with watching TV. After that I&#39;d settle in front of the TV with the wife and we&#39;d watch a show that we both enjoy (so not the sci-fi I&#39;d typically watch while I row). At around 10pm I&#39;d be off to bed, but would typically read again for up to an hour.</p><h3>Reading</h3><p>I read around 45 books per year, mostly fiction, and mostly space operas, although recently I&#39;ve started to read more non-fiction. I&#39;d always struggled to read non-fiction, until I started reading in the mornings, I find that reading non-fiction in the morning, and fiction in the evenings really suits me, so it&#39;s something I&#39;m planning to continue. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/30515830-mark-evans'>Follow me via Goodreads.</a></p><h3>Exercise</h3><p>I exercise for 2hrs per day. On the face of it this might seem like a lot, its not. When you consider that I&#39;m basically <strong>not moving for the other 22hrs (sleeping or at my desk) then moving for 2hrs each day actually doesn&#39;t feel like it&#39;s enough</strong>. And I think this is one of the most important things I&#39;ve learnt from working from home for almost a year. I no longer walk to the train, or from the tube to the office, or around the office, or go outside to buy my lunch. The only exercise I now do is via planned exercise sessions i.e. walking, running, or rowing. Apart from those activities, there&#39;s very little else I do that&#39;s burning calories. For this reason <strong>I&#39;d suggest that 2hrs of exercise each day is probably a minimum for anyone who&#39;s working from home 5 days a week</strong>. <a href='https://www.strava.com/athletes/10904388'>Follow me via Strava.</a></p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>I don&#39;t know what&#39;s going to happen once this pandemic is over. There&#39;s a lot of discussion about us never returning to the previous office routines, and I&#39;m all in favour of not going back to the old ways. Working from home suits me, and to be honest, I think it suits employers, as I think most employees are more productive (not to mention the costs my employer must be saving on office space and reduced travel).</p><hr><h4>What is OnlyRSS?</h4><p>OnlyRSS is a collection of articles that exist only in the RSS feed itself. There&#39;s no CMS used for article creation\storage, and there&#39;s no website where articles can be viewed, the articles can only be viewed in RSS Aggregators such as <a href='http://feedly.com'>Feedly</a> and <a href='http://inoreader.com'>Inoreader</a>. If you have any comments on this article, or any questions about OnlyRSS, then please ask me (Mark Evans) via <a href='https://twitter.com/dbs_sticky'>Twitter.</a></p>



]]>            </description>
        </item>        <!-- Using Virtual Desktops in Windows 10 -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article2</guid>
            <title>Using Virtual Desktops in Windows 10</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/using-virtual-desktops-in-windows-10.html</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 15:00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>            <!-- article contents -->
            <description><![CDATA[
	

<h3>A typical day</h3><p>On any typical workday I might have the following applications open on my PC:</P><p>Tasks (Outlook for Web), Agenda (Outlook for Web), Email (Outlook for Web), MS Teams (chats and meetings), Journal (Excel, where I document my activities), WhatsApp (non-work chat), Signal (non-work chat), Feedly (news aggregator), BBC.co.uk (news), Confluence (User Stories), JIRA (backlog), Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Adobe Analytics (product analytics),Tableau (product analytics), Axure or Excalidraw (prototyping & sketching).</P><p>In turns out that these applications fit quite nicely into groups, where each group is based around different tasks:</p><ol><li><strong>Plan, record, and communicate</strong> (Tasks, Agenda, Email, MS Teams, Journal)</li><li><strong>Taking a break</strong> (WhatsApp, Signal, Feedly, BBC News)</li><li><strong>Monthly reporting</strong> (Tableau, Adobe Analytics, Excel)</li><li><strong>User Story creation</strong> (Confluence, JIRA, Axure or Excalidraw)</li></ol><p>1 & 2 are 'reference tasks', I need these open all day as I'll check them frequently, 3 & 4 are examples of 'focused tasks', this is where I'd spend the majority of my day (I'd typically never have more than 2 of these on the go at the same time). Each of the above task groups is mutually exclusive. I'm either drafting my monthly report or taking a break, I'm not documenting a User Story while also communicating with a colleague via MS Teams. Many of the apps within each task group benefits from being visible at the same time e.g. when I'm planning my day it's good to see my task list and agenda side-by-side, when I'm checking to see who is trying to contact me, it's good to see emails and MS Teams open at the same time. Taking the above into account, you end up with the following basic requirements:</P><ol><li>The ability to group multiple apps together (by task). i.e. form 'task groups'.</li><li>The ability to view apps side-by-side within the task groups.</li><li>The ability to only view one task group at a time.</li><li>The ability to quickly switch between task groups.</li><li>The Windows Taskbar is poorly named.</li></ol><p>The Windows Taskbar does not show you a list of tasks, it shows you a list of apps (it's an "App bar"), and as I mention above, planning my day requires 2 apps, writing my monthly report requires 3 apps. There is no real task switcher in Windows i.e. there's nothing that allows you to easily switch between groups of apps (I think Windows Sets was Microsoft's proposed solution to this, it would have satisfied requirements 1, 3 & 4 from the list above....but not 2. But, it currently looks like Sets is not going to become a feature in Windows 10).</p><h3>Enter Virtual Desktops!</h3><p>First, let's start with a definition of what a virtual desktop is:</p><blockquote>In computing, a virtual desktop is a term used with respect to user interfaces to describe ways in which the virtual space of a computer's desktop environment is expanded beyond the physical limits of the screen's display area through the use of software. This compensates for a limited desktop area and can also be helpful in reducing clutter.</blockquote><p>Although virtual desktops have been around since the late 1980s, they were not available natively in Windows until the launch of Windows 10. Because virtual desktops are discrete, make full use of the real desktop, and allow fast switching via keyboard shortcuts, they satisfy all 4 requirements from my list.</p><h4>An example</h4><p>To keep things simple, I'm going to assume that I'm only working on a single focused task and am not taking any breaks. This leaves me with only two task groups required for my day i.e. 1) plan, record & communicate, 2) monthly reporting. For me, these task groups would look like those displayed in the image below:</p><img src="/images/article2figure1.png" alt="sketch of dual displays" width="1938" height="377"><p>As I have a dual monitor setup, each virtual desktop includes both monitors. My first virtual desktop includes three web instances of Outlook (tasks, calendar, and emails), MS Teams (for chat and meetings), and Excel (for my journal). The second virtual desktop includes a web browser (product analytics via Adobe Analytics and Tableau) and Excel (monthly report). All the apps are open and sized appropriately, so there's no need to switch between, minimise, maximise, resize, or drag any windows. The only "window management" that's required is via the keyboard shortcuts that enable moving between virtual desktops i.e. Ctrl+Win+LeftArrow and Ctrl+Win+RightArrow. And it's this change that I believe is what makes virtual desktops so valuable.</p><p>It was only when I started to use virtual desktops in this way that I realised how much time I was spending scanning the taskbar looking for apps, moving them around, resizing them, and opening and closing them. And I was repeating this process multiple times per day as I was switching between tasks. With virtual desktops, I'll set up my reference desktop as soon as I start my day, I'll check for any unread emails, and see what meetings and tasks I have scheduled, once that's done, I'll then setup my focused desktop. Every 1/2 hour or so I'll quickly switch back to my reference desktop to see if there are any new messages or meeting requests, if not, I'll jump straight back into my focused desktop. The process of switching takes less than a second, and I've not had to hunt and peck at the Taskbar, or do any window managed to achieve this.</p><p>Even in this simple example with only 2 task groups, I've saved myself a lot of window management, but, typically I'd have 4 virtual desktops on the go, I'd have my 'taking a break' group, and sometimes a second focused group (I find it hard to focus on a single task for 8 hours, so I like to switch between two different tasks whenever possible).</p><h3>Using Windows Virtual Desktops</h3><p>To create a virtual desktop, click the Task View icon located on the Taskbar (or use the shortcut Win + Tab), then, in the top left corner, select "New desktop". To move between these 2 desktops, use Ctrl+Win+LeftArrow and Ctrl+Win+RightArrow.</p><p>While in the Task View, you can also drag apps into the virtual desktops, or right click the app and select "move to", to move apps between virtual desktops.</p><img src="/images/article2figure2.png" alt="sketch of dual displays" width="1938" height="377"><h3>What if I only have a small single display?</h3><p>If you are limited to a single small display, then it's likely that you are running your apps maximised and using the Taskbar to quickly switch between them. If this is the case, then virtual desktops aren't going to provide you with any extra utility (at least not as far as I can tell, if you've found them useful in this scenario, then let me know).</p><h3>Summary</h3><p>Virtual Desktops might not be for everyone, but since using them I've been surprised at how much more efficient I find my app management on Windows. Virtual Desktops is something I'll be sticking with, and I'm hoping that Microsoft continue to build on this new Windows 10 feature.</p>


]]>            </description>
        </item>        <!-- What even is OnlyRSS? -->
        <item>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">article1</guid>
            <title>What is OnlyRSS?</title>
            <link>https://onlyrss.org/posts/about.html</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[

<p>I've been using RSS feeds to aggregate web content for almost 20 years. I believe that having relevant content available in a single location makes the web a much better experience and makes me a far more productive and more knowledgeable person\employee. Unfortunately, many “modern” websites don’t support RSS, so I’m fighting back. To help readdress the balance, I’m publishing my blog articles as an RSS feed only. There’s no destination website (or CMS), the RSS feed will contain the entire article.</p><p>What does this mean? Well, for a start it makes my articles very difficult to find (and I’m ok with that), and it means that you (the subscriber) has full control over the reading experience via your RSS aggregator of choice.</p><p>I’ll probably only add an article once a month, and those articles will be on things that interest me and that I think might interest others, e.g., Data Viz, RSS, News BI tools, productivity tools etc.</p><p>If you see something in an article and want to comment, look me up on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/dbs_sticky">@dbs_sticky (MarkEvans)</a></p>


]]>            </description>
        </item>        <!-- End of Blog articles --></channel>
</rss>